<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % manualent SYSTEM "manual.ent">
%manualent;
]>
<chapter xml:id="ch-alix-board-setup"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en">
  <title>ALIX Board Setup</title>

  <section xml:id="sec-booting-connecting">
    <title>Booting and connecting</title>

    <para>The first thing to do with your ALIX board is to boot it up and
    hook it up to it with a serial terminal.  Connect your workstation's
    serial port (or, as in my case, USB-to-serial adapter) to the board's
    port with an FF null modem cable.  The default serial port settings
    used by the ALIX.2D3's BIOS are 38400 baud with eight data bits, one
    stop bit, no parity, and XON/XOFF flow control; provide these settings
    to <command>cu(1)</command> or your other serial communications program
    of choice, then connect, e.g.:</para>

<screen width="80">
$ cu -e -o -s 38400 -l /dev/ttyUSB0
</screen>

    <para>Now plug in the ALIX's power supply.  You should immediately
    see BIOS messages appear on your serial terminal, followed by a
    memory test, and finally an error message about an invalid disk.  So
    good, so far.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-bios-configuration">
    <title>BIOS configuration</title>

    <para>Reboot the ALIX board with your serial terminal still connected.
    This time press <keycap>s</keycap> during the BIOS memory check in
    order to enter the tinyBIOS configuration utility.  Press the number
    <keycap>1</keycap> to change the BIOS's serial console rate to 115200
    baud (in order to make serial file transfers bearable, if necessary),
    <keycap>L</keycap> to enable LBA mode on the CF card, and then
    <keycap>U</keycap> to enable Ultra DMA.  Also press <keycap>E</keycap>
    to enable PXE booting.  Finally, press <keycap>Q</keycap> to quit.
    When prompted, confirm that you wish to persist these changes to
    flash.</para>

    <para>Disconnect your serial terminal, then reconfigure your terminal
    software to communicate with the ALIX board at the new rate of 115200
    baud.  Reconnect your null modem cable and ensure that everything is
    still working.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-clock-battery">
    <title>CMOS clock battery</title>

    <para>Unless ordered with a special build option, the ALIX.2D3 board
    lacks a backup battery (such as those found in most general-purpose
    PCs) to keep its CMOS clock running while the board is disconnected
    from its power supply.  Fortunately, the board comes ready for one to
    be installed; just solder a standard CR2032 horizontal battery holder
    into the spot on the circuit board marked "BT1," being sure to observe
    correct polarity.  Install a fresh battery in the holder and you will
    be good to go.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
