<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % manualent SYSTEM "manual.ent">
%manualent;
]>
<chapter xml:id="ch-introduction"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section xml:id="sec-purpose">
    <title>Purpose and target audience</title>

    <para>This document is a start-to-end guide to setting up a <link
    xlink:href="http://www.pcengines.ch/alix2d3.htm">PC Engines GmbH
    ALIX.2D3</link> system board as an OpenBSD &obsdVer;-based NAT gateway,
    providing a small LAN with a PF NAT/firewall, recursive DNS service,
    Network Time Protocol synchronization, and more.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-alix">
      <title>An ALIX as an OpenBSD router</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/alix-enclosed.jpg" format="jpg" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>First and foremost, I'm writing this for my own future reference.
    Therefore I will assume of the reader some experience with Unix
    (although not necessarily OpenBSD) system administration, as well as a
    general understanding of TCP/IP and IPv6 networking.</para>

    <para>But I also want this guide to be useful to others out there,
    which is why I'm bothering to publish it at all.  Even though it
    necessarily addresses some particulars of my installation, I have tried
    to keep it as general as possible.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-why-openbsd">
    <title>Why OpenBSD?</title>

    <para>Why build a router on OpenBSD, rather than more popular open
    source source operating systems such as Debian Linux?  It ultimately
    comes down to personal tastes – Linux as well as any of the other BSDs
    are plenty capable of getting this job done – but these are the
    specific advantages that led me to choose OpenBSD for this application:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Like the other BSDs, OpenBSD's development model is as a
        single, cohesive operating system rather than the collection of
        disparate parts that makes up most Linux distributions.  In my
        experience this makes for a smoother system administration
        experience: all the man pages are kept relevant and up to date, and
        system utilities make sense in the context of the system as a
        whole.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>There is a strong emphasis on security and code correctness
        in the OpenBSD community, making the system uniquely suited for use
        on a router with constant exposure to a hostile Internet.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>OpenBSD is especially focused on networking.  The base system
        includes great networking software like the
        <command>pf(4)</command> firewall, <command>altq(9)</command> queue
        management, the <command>pppoe(4)</command> kernel driver,
        <command>dhcpd(8)</command>, and <command>named(8)</command>.
        Widely used software like OpenSSH and OpenNTPD actually originates
        with the OpenBSD project, and so is perhaps better integrated into
        OpenBSD than in any other operating system.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>OpenBSD is very light on system resources, with lower memory
        use than Debian Linux.  This is good for limited memory systems
        like the ALIX board.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The ports tree offers easier customization of third-party
        software than the binary package mechanisms in most Linux
        distributions.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-intro-installation-type">
    <title>OpenBSD installation type</title>

    <para>The end product of this guide is a full, general-purpose OpenBSD
    installation on the ALIX board's Compact Flash card.  Specifically,
    this is in contrast to a read-only, image-based OpenBSD installation
    such as offered by <link
    xlink:href="http://www.nmedia.net/flashrd/">flashrd</link>.  There are
    some good reasons to use flashrd rather than a traditional OpenBSD
    install on systems like this:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>flashrd allows you to prepare an OpenBSD image on a PC and
	then dd it onto a flash card for the router, bypassing the
	complexity of installation by PXE boot.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>flashrd's file-based update mechanism makes remote system
	updates easy and safe.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>A flashrd-based system will generally run with the root
	filesystem mounted read-only, making the system more resilient
	against unexpected shutdowns.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Nevertheless, I prefer a traditional OpenBSD installation for
    this project: the router sits in my living room, so I don't have to
    worry about the remote upgrade situation, and it runs on a UPS so power
    outages are not an issue.</para>

    <para>One concern some people may have is the risk of extended flash
    wear to a CF card mounted in read/write mode.  In practice I have not
    found this to be an issue; for what it's worth, I've been running this
    router on the same CF card for about four years now with no flash
    failure.  Besides, even with flashrd one cannot avoid
    <emphasis>all</emphasis> flash writes.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-prerequisites">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>If you want to follow along with these instructions, you will
    need to have a few things before you begin:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A cable Internet connection (with DOCSIS cable modem already
        set up)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>ALIX.2D3 board with power supply and, optionally, enclosure</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>32 GB Compact Flash card<footnote><para>While any 4 GB or
        larger Compact Flash card should easily suffice (and much smaller
        can be managed, depending on how much effort you are willing to
        expend paring down the OpenBSD operating system, and the exact
        nature of your requirements), the disk partition scheme described
        in this document assumes the use of 32 GB
        media.</para></footnote></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Two Ethernet (Cat 5e or Cat 6 with 8P8C connectors) cables</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>RS-232 null modem cable (female-female)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A PC workstation with: an RS-232 serial port (or a
        USB-to-serial adapter) and an ethernet adapter</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


    <para>Additionally, if your ALIX.2D3 board does not already include a
    battery backup for its CMOS clock (a custom build option for this
    board, also known as the <link
    xlink:href="http://www.pcengines.ch/alix2d13.htm">ALIX.2D13</link>) and
    you wish to add one, you will need the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>One CR2032 battery</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Soldering supplies and equipment: iron, solder, sponge, etc.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>CR2032 battery holder with 20.4mm lead spacing<footnote>
        <para>For instance, <link
        xlink:href="http://octopart.com/cr2032+mfr+fh1-renata-18985577">Renata
        CR2032FH1</link> or <link
        xlink:href="http://octopart.com/br2032-1he-panasonic-155416">Panasonic
        BR2032-1HE</link>, as per the ALIX.2D3
        documentation.</para></footnote>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Installation of the CR2032 battery holder will be covered in <xref linkend="ch-alix-board-setup" />.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-intro-conventions">
    <title>Conventions used in this document</title>

    <para>Certain file listings and instructions in this guide necessarily
    refer to specifics such as hostname or private (RFC 1918) IPv4
    addresses.  Wherever you see these, substitute values appropriate for
    your own setup for those shown in <xref linkend="tab-specifics"
    />.</para>

    <table xml:id="tab-specifics" frame="all">
      <title>Installation specifics</title>
      <tgroup cols="2" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Setting</entry>
            <entry>Value</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Router hostname</entry>
            <entry>midgard.example.net</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Unix username</entry>
            <entry>mshroyer</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Router IPv4 address on LAN</entry>
            <entry>10.19.0.1</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Private IPv4 network block</entry>
            <entry>10.19.0.0/17</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>Throughout this document, OpenBSD commands and system components
    are referred to by name, followed in parentheses by the section number
    in the OpenBSD manual in which their documentation lives.  For example,
    the classic Unix text editor would be shown as
    <command>vi(1)</command>.</para>
    
  </section>
</chapter>
