<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % manualent SYSTEM "manual.ent">
%manualent;
]>
<chapter xml:id="ch-openbsd-installation"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en">
  <title>OpenBSD Installation</title>

  <section xml:id="sec-pxe-server">
    <title>Boot server setup</title>

    <para>Installing OpenBSD on the ALIX.2D3 is a little more involved than
    installing on standard PC hardware, due to the lack of a video card or
    the ability to boot from CD-ROM (even from USB CD-ROM devices).
    Instead we will have to use the ALIX board's PXE boot capability to
    boot into the installer, by running a PXE boot server on the PC
    mentioned in <xref linkend="sec-prerequisites" />.</para>

    <para>Thankfully, the Fedora 18 desktop live CD is flexible enough to
    provide this temporary boot server without requiring any permanent
    changes to your PC.  The server will run PXE (appropriately configured
    DHCP and TFTP) services, along with an FTP server for providing OpenBSD
    system sets to the installer without requiring the target system to be
    able to route out to the wider Internet.</para>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-fedora-packages">
      <title>Fedora packages</title>

      <para>Boot the Fedora live CD and click on "Try Fedora."  Ensure the
      system has a working Internet connection, then open a terminal and
      invoke yum to install prerequisite packages:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora$ su
fedora# yum install dnsmasq vsftpd uucp</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-openbsd-files">
      <title>OpenBSD installation files</title>

      <para>For PXE booting, you will need to serve the pxeboot bootstrap
      and bsd.rd ramdisk kernel via TFTP.  Make a directory to serve as the
      TFTP root and copy these there from your favorite
      mirror:<footnote><para>If you've purchased an OpenBSD CD set, you can
      find the files there instead, of course.</para></footnote></para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# mkdir -p /var/tftp
fedora# cd /var/tftp
fedora# lftp
lftp :~> open ftp3.usa.openbsd.org
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:~> cd /pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386> mget pxeboot bsd.rd
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386> quit
fedora#</screen>

      <para>Once the installer is running from bsd.rd, it will need to
      fetch the OpenBSD system sets.  So likewise, copy these into an FTP
      directory:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# mkdir -p /var/ftp/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386
fedora# cd /var/ftp/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386
lftp :~> open ftp3.usa.openbsd.org
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:~> cd /pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386> mget *.tgz
lftp ftp3.usa.openbsd.org:/pub/OpenBSD/5.2/i386> quit
fedora#</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-network-config">
      <title>Host system configuration</title>

      <para>As configured out of the box, certain Fedora system processes
      will get in the way of the PXE server: default SELinux policies will
      prevent dnsmasq from serving files from
      <filename>/var/tftp</filename>, firewall rules will hinder access to
      the DHCP service, and NetworkManager will interfere with the IP
      address configuration of your Ethernet interface.  As this is only a
      live CD, it is simplest to just disable these problematic services
      and get on with it:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# setenforce 0
fedora# systemctl stop firewalld.service
fedora# systemctl stop NetworkManager.service</screen>

      <para>If your computer accesses your LAN through its Ethernet port,
      disconnect it from your LAN now.  Run this command to configure a
      static address on the PC's Ethernet interface, substituting your own
      interface's name in place of em1:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# ip link set up dev em1
fedora# ip addr change 192.168.2.1/24 dev em1</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-dhcp-tftp-server">
      <title>DHCP and TFTP server</title>

      <para>Replace <filename>/etc/dnsmasq.conf</filename> with the
      following:</para>

<programlisting>
dhcp-range=192.168.2.50,192.168.2.150,12h
dhcp-boot=pxeboot
enable-tftp
tftp-root=/var/tftp
</programlisting>

      <para>Now you can start the DHCP and TFTP server.</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# systemctl start dnsmasq.service</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-ftp-server">
      <title>FTP server</title>

      <para>The Fedora package for vsftpd is configured to serve out of
      <filename>/var/ftp</filename> by default, so no special configuration
      is needed.  Just start the daemon:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# systemctl start vsftpd.service</screen>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-pxe-serial-console">
      <title>Serial console</title>

      <para>Connect your laptop's serial port (or USB-serial adapter) to
      the ALIX board's serial port with your null modem cable, then use the
      <command>cu</command> command to open the serial console.  For
      example, if you're using a USB adapter:</para>

<screen width="80">
fedora# cu -e -o -s 115200 -l /dev/ttyUSB0</screen>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-pxe-booting">
    <title>PXE booting the ALIX</title>

    <para>With your serial console ready, plug in the ALIX board's power
    adapter, and you should see the board begin to boot.  Enter the
    following at the OpenBSD boot menu:</para>

<screen width="80">
boot> stty com0 115200
boot> set tty com0
boot> bsd.rd</screen>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-openbsd-installer">
    <title>The OpenBSD installer</title>

    <section xml:id="sec-openbsd-installer-basic">
      <title>Basic setup</title>

      <para>When the OpenBSD ramdisk boots, you will be prompted with the
      choices: <prompt>(I)nstall, (U)pgrade, or (S)hell?</prompt> – press the
      <keycap>I</keycap> key to begin the installer.  Therein you will be
      asked a few preliminary questions.</para>

      <procedure>
        <step>
          <para>Enter the desired hostname.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Configure IPv4 on the vr0 interface, but skip IPv6
          configuration for now.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Choose and enter a root password.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Opt to start <command>sshd(8)</command> and
          <command>ntpd(8)</command> by default.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Specify that you do not expect to run the X Window System.
          This will cause the machdep.allowaperature sysctl to be disabled,
          possibly improving your system's security.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Set the default console to com0.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Skip setting up a regular user account for now.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>Enter your timezone.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-openbsd-partitioning">
      <title>Partitioning</title>

      <para>Next you will need to set up your disk partitions and slices.
      In <command>fdisk(8)</command>, specify that you want to use the
      whole disk for OpenBSD.  Then you will be brought to the BSD disk
      label editor.</para>

      <para>Press <keycap>P</keycap> to view the disk's current BSD slices;
      you shouldn't see anything here except the "c" slice, which
      represents the entire disk.  Use the <keycap>A</keycap> command to
      create the disk slice set shown in <xref
      linkend="tab-openbsd-slices"/>.</para>

      <table xml:id="tab-openbsd-slices" frame="all">
        <title>OpenBSD disk slices</title>
        <tgroup cols="5" align="left" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Label</entry>
              <entry>FS Type</entry>
              <entry>Mount Point</entry>
              <entry>Blocks</entry>
              <entry>Bytes</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>wd0a</entry>
              <entry>4.2BSD</entry>
              <entry>/</entry>
              <entry>1,048,576</entry>
              <entry>512 MB</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>wd0d</entry>
              <entry>4.2BSD</entry>
              <entry>/tmp</entry>
              <entry>1,048,576</entry>
              <entry>512 MB</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>wd0e</entry>
              <entry>4.2BSD</entry>
              <entry>/var</entry>
              <entry>6,291,456</entry>
              <entry>3 GB</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>wd0f</entry>
              <entry>4.2BSD</entry>
              <entry>/usr</entry>
              <entry>20,971,520</entry>
              <entry>10 GB</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>wd0g</entry>
              <entry>4.2BSD</entry>
              <entry>/home</entry>
              <entry>2,159,338</entry>
              <entry>1.03 GB</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>When that is done, press <keycap>Q</keycap> to quit the label
      editor, then press <keycap>Y</keycap> to confirm that you wish to
      write the new disk label.  Confirm your way past any relevant warning
      messages, and the CF card will be partitioned and formatted for
      OpenBSD's installation.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-openbsd-sets">
      <title>Installation sets</title>

      <para>Next you will be asked where to find the OpenBSD installation
      sets: choose the default mechanism, http, and use the default OpenBSD
      mirror (or any other mirror of your choice).  Make any desired
      changes to the default set selection and then proceed to the next
      stage of the installer.<footnote><para>I have heard it said that it
      is a good idea to install all of the OpenBSD sets if one wants to
      build packages from the ports tree, even if one does not intend to
      run X11.  However, I have not found this to be necessary in my own
      experience.</para></footnote></para>

      <para>Once the sets have been installed, you can shut down your
      Ubuntu PXE boot server and reboot the ALIX board into its new OpenBSD
      installation.  You may also wish to disable PXE booting in the ALIX's
      BIOS while you are not using it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
