<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY % manualent SYSTEM "manual.ent">
%manualent;
]>
<chapter xml:id="ch-ports-packages"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         version="5.0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xml:lang="en">
  <title>Ports and Packages</title>

  <para>Subsequent sections of this guide will entail installing various
  bits of third-party software in order to augment the router's
  functionality.  Much of this software will be available through the
  OpenBSD Ports Collection and package repositories.</para>

  <para>This section describes how to configure your system to install
  software from both the OpenBSD binary package repositories and the ports
  tree.  Readers already familiar with OpenBSD system administration may
  wish to skip over this section.</para>

  <section xml:id="sec-packages">
    <title>OpenBSD packages</title>

    <para>OpenBSD packages are bundles of pre-compiled third party
    software.  There are made available on OpenBSD FTP and HTTP mirrors,
    organized by OpenBSD version and machine architecture.  For i386
    machines like the ALIX, the relevant mirror directory is
    <filename>/pub/OpenBSD/&obsdVer;/packages/i386/</filename>.</para>

    <para>To use a package repository, set the environment variable
    <code>PKG_PATH</code> to a URL pointing to your favorite repository.  A
    full list of repository mirrors can be found here:</para>

    <para><link xlink:href="http://www.openbsd.org/ftp.html">http://www.openbsd.org/ftp.html</link></para>

    <para>You'll probably want to put this in your shell's startup script,
    so this gets set automatically when you log in:</para>

<programlisting>
# PKG_PATH="ftp://ftp3.usa.openbsd.org/pub/OpenBSD/&obsdVer;/packages/i386/"
# export PKG_PATH
</programlisting>

    <para>Now you can use the <command>pkg_add(1)</command> command to add
    new packages to your system from the mirror, e.g.:</para>

<screen width="80">
# pkg_add -r pftop
</screen>

    <para>A list of all currently installed packages can be obtained with
    the <command>pkg_info(1)</command> command.  Note that this list will
    include software installed from the ports tree, as well: when you build
    and install a port, you are actually creating a package which is then
    installed on your system; see <xref linkend="sec-ports" /> for details.
    This has the nice result that you can upgrade an application that was
    installed from the ports tree to a newer version from a package
    repository, or vice-versa.</para>

    <para>Refer to the <command>packages(7)</command> man page for more
    information about installing, updating, and removing OpenBSD
    package.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-ports">
    <title>OpenBSD ports</title>

    <para>The OpenBSD Ports Collection provides an easy, uniform way to
    configure, build, and install third-party open source applications on
    your OpenBSD system.  Each "port" consists of a directory with (among
    other things) any operating system-specific patches for the
    application, and a Makefile whose default target will automatically
    download the software's source code, verify the download against known
    checksums, apply the patches, and the compile the software into a
    binary package – after recursively doing the same for any missing
    prerequisites.  The compiled binary package can then be installed by
    running <command>make install</command> in the port directory.</para>

    <para>Ports are organized in a directory hierarchy called the "ports
    tree."  A copy of this tree must be installed on your system in order
    to build ports.</para>

    <section xml:id="sec-ports-installing">
      <title>Installing the Ports Collection</title>

      <para>Like the rest of the OpenBSD project, the OpenBSD Ports tree is
      maintained in a public CVS repository.  It can be obtained and
      updated via CVS checkouts, or by downloading tarballs of CVS
      snapshots from an FTP or HTTP mirror.  However, the former option is
      terribly slow, and the latter doesn't lend itself well to keeping
      your copy of the tree up-to-date.</para>

      <para>Instead we can use <link
      xlink:href="http://www.cvsup.org/">CVSup</link> protocol to quickly
      check out and update the entire Ports tree from any of the public
      OpenBSD CVSup servers, which are listed here:</para>

      <para><link xlink:href="http://www.openbsd.org/cvsup.html#CVSROOT">http://www.openbsd.org/cvsup.html#CVSROOT</link></para>

      <para>First you'll need the <command>cvsup(1)</command> program,
      which is not included in the OpenBSD base system.  It is available as
      a binary package, however:</para>

<screen width="80">
# pkg_add -r cvsup-16.1hp2-no_x11
</screen>

      <para>Next, create a file <filename>/etc/cvsup-file-ports</filename>
      with the following configuration, substituting any <link
      xlink:href="http://www.openbsd.org/cvsup.html#CVSROOT">CVSup
      mirror</link> of your choice for
      <code>cvsup.no.openbsd.org</code>:</para>

      <programlisting><xi:include href="files/etc/cvsup-file-ports" parse="text" /></programlisting>

      <para>Now you can use <command>cvsup(1)</command> to fetch and
      install the tree:</para>

<screen width="80">
# cvsup -g -L 2 /etc/cvsup-file-ports
</screen>

      <para>Downloading the entire tree will take a while, but subsequent
      updates (performed using the same command as shown above) will be
      quick.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec-ports-using">
      <title>Using ports</title>

      <para>In most cases, to install software from the Ports tree you need
      only change to its directory under <filename>/usr/ports</filename>
      and <command>make install</command> it.  For example, supposing that
      you want to install Bash, you would perform the following:</para>

<screen width="80"><![CDATA[
# cd /usr/ports/shells/bash
# make && make install
]]></screen>

      <para>And the software will be automatically downloaded, patched,
      configured, compiled, and then installed into the
      <filename>/usr/local</filename> hierarchy.  This overview barely
      scratches the surface of the Ports Collection's capabilities,
      however; for more information, including how to specify custom Port
      build options, refer to the <command>ports(7)</command> man
      page.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-ports-packages-caveats">
    <title>Some caveats</title>

    <para>While OpenBSD's package repositories and Ports tree are extremely
    useful, there are some shortcomings to be aware of when using
    them:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>The package repositories do not contain all the
        software and all the possible combinations of build options to be
        found in the Ports Collection.</emphasis> Also, the package
        repositories may not be as up-to-date as the latest checkout of the
        Ports tree.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Software in the package repositories is not
        cryptographically signed.</emphasis> In addition to the
        trustworthiness of the third-party software itself, you must also
        consider the security of the package mirror
        itself.<footnote><para>This is not merely a theoretical risk.  In
        August 2007, five of the core Ubuntu Linux FTP mirrors had to be
        taken offline when they were found to have been compromised.
        Ubuntu users were never in any danger from this, however, because
        the packages in Ubuntu's apt repositories are cryptographically
        signed.</para></footnote></para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Likewise, the Ports tree mirrors are not
        signed.</emphasis> However, MD5 and SHA1 hashes of ports' source
        distributions are included in the Ports tree, so assuming you have
        a genuine copy of the Ports tree there is little risk of installing
        compromised third-party packages.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
